<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--  $Id$ -->
<chapter id="search-mapping" revision="3">
  <title>Mapping entities to the index structure</title>

  <para>All the metadata information needed to index entities is described
  through some Java annotations. There is no need for xml mapping files nor a
  list of indexed entities. The list is discovered at startup time scanning
  the Hibernate mapped entities.</para>

  <section id="search-mapping-entity" revision="3">
    <title>Mapping an entity</title>

    <section>
      <title>Basic mapping</title>

      <para>First, we must declare a persistent class as indexable. This is
      done by annotating the class with <literal>@Indexed</literal> (all
      entities not annotated with <literal>@Indexed</literal> will be ignored
      by the indexing process):</para>

      <programlisting>@Entity
<emphasis role="bold">@Indexed(index="indexes/essays")</emphasis>
public class Essay {
    ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>The <literal>index</literal> attribute tells Hibernate what the
      Lucene directory name is (usually a directory on your file system). If
      you wish to define a base directory for all Lucene indexes, you can use
      the <literal>hibernate.search.default.indexBase</literal> property in
      your configuration file. Each entity instance will be represented by a
      Lucene <classname>Document</classname> inside the given index (aka
      Directory).</para>

      <para>For each property (or attribute) of your entity, you have the
      ability to describe how it will be indexed. The default (ie no
      annotation) means that the property is completly ignored by the indexing
      process. <literal>@Field</literal> does declare a property as indexed.
      When indexing an element to a Lucene document you can specify how it is
      indexed:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><literal>name</literal> : describe under which name, the
          property should be stored in the Lucene Document. The default value
          is the property name (following the JavaBeans convention)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>store</literal> : describe whether or not the
          property is stored in the Lucene index. You can store the value
          <literal>Store.YES</literal> (comsuming more space in the index but
          allowing projection, see <xref linkend="projections" /> for more
          information), store it in a compressed way
          <literal>Store.COMPRESS</literal> (this does consume more CPU), or
          avoid any storage <literal>Store.NO</literal> (this is the default
          value). When a property is stored, you can retrieve it from the
          Lucene Document (note that this is not related to whether the
          element is indexed or not).</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>index: describe how the element is indexed (ie the process
          used to index the property and the type of information store). The
          different values are <literal>Index.NO</literal> (no indexing, ie
          cannot be found by a query), <literal>Index.TOKENIZED</literal> (use
          an analyzer to process the property),
          <literal>Index.UN_TOKENISED</literal> (no analyzer pre processing),
          <literal>Index.NO_NORM</literal> (do not store the normalization
          data).</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>These attributes are part of the <literal>@Field</literal>
      annotation.</para>

      <para>Whether or not you want to store the data depends on how you wish
      to use the index query result. For a regular Hibernate Search usage,
      storing is not necessary. However you might want to store some fields to
      subsequently project them (see <xref linkend="projections" /> for more
      information).</para>

      <para>Whether or not you want to tokenize a property depends on whether
      you wish to search the element as is, or by the words it contains. It
      make sense to tokenize a text field, but it does not to do it for a date
      field (or an id field). Note that fields used for sorting must not be
      tokenized.</para>

      <para>Finally, the id property of an entity is a special property used
      by Hibernate Search to ensure index unicity of a given entity. By
      design, an id has to be stored and must not be tokenized. To mark a
      property as index id, use the <literal>@DocumentId</literal>
      annotation.</para>

      <programlisting>@Entity
@Indexed(index="indexes/essays")
public class Essay {
    ...

    @Id
    <emphasis role="bold">@DocumentId</emphasis>
    public Long getId() { return id; }

    <emphasis role="bold">@Field(name="Abstract", index=Index.TOKENIZED, store=Store.YES)</emphasis>
    public String getSummary() { return summary; }

    @Lob
    <emphasis role="bold">@Field(index=Index.TOKENIZED)</emphasis>
    public String getText() { return text; }
}</programlisting>

      <para>These annotations define an index with three fields:
      <literal>id</literal> , <literal>Abstract</literal> and
      <literal>text</literal> . Note that by default the field name is
      decapitalized, following the JavaBean specification.</para>

      <note>
        <para>You <emphasis>must</emphasis> specify
        <literal>@DocumentId</literal> on the identifier property of your
        entity class.</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Mapping properties multiple times</title>

      <para>It is sometimes needed to map a property multiple times per index,
      with slightly different indexing strategies. Especially, sorting a query
      by field requires the field to be <literal>UN_TOKENIZED</literal>. If
      one want to search by words in this property and still sort it, one need
      to index it twice, once tokenized, once untokenized. @Fields allows to
      achieve this goal.</para>

      <programlisting>@Entity
@Indexed(index = "Book" )
public class Book {
    @Fields( {
            @Field(index = Index.TOKENIZED),
            @Field(name = "summary_forSort", index = Index.UN_TOKENIZED, store = Store.YES)
            } )
    public String getSummary() {
        return summary;
    }

    ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>The field summary is indexed twice, once as
      <literal>summary</literal> in a tokenized way, and once as
      <literal>summary_forSort</literal> in an untokenized way. @Field
      supports 2 attributes useful when @Fields is used:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>analyzer: defines a @Analyzer annotation per field rather than
          per property</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>bridge: defines a @FieldBridge annotation per field rather
          than per property</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>See below for more information about analyzers and field
      bridges.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Embedded and associated objects</title>

      <para>Associated objects as well as embedded objects can be indexed as
      part of the root entity index.</para>

      <programlisting>@Entity
@Indexed
public class Place {
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue
    @DocumentId
    private Long id;

    @Field( index = Index.TOKENIZED )
    private String name;

    @OneToOne( cascade = { CascadeType.PERSIST, CascadeType.REMOVE } )
    <emphasis role="bold">@IndexedEmbedded</emphasis>
    private Address address;
    ....
}

@Entity
@Indexed
public class Address {
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue
    @DocumentId
    private Long id;

    @Field(index=Index.TOKENIZED)
    private String street;

    @Field(index=Index.TOKENIZED)
    private String city;

    <emphasis role="bold">@ContainedIn</emphasis>
    @OneToMany(mappedBy="address")
    private Set&lt;Place&gt; places;
    ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>In this example, the place fields will be indexed in the
      <literal>Place</literal> index. The <literal>Place</literal> index
      documents will also contain the fields <literal>address.id</literal>,
      <literal>address.street</literal>, and <literal>address.city</literal>
      which you will be able to query. This is enabled by the
      <literal>@IndexedEmbedded</literal> annotation.</para>

      <para><literal>@ContainedIn</literal> is useful on embedded objects that
      are also entities (like <literal>Address</literal> in this example): it
      basically means that when an address entity is updated, the index
      document of the associated <literal>Place</literal>(s), also have to be
      updated.</para>

      <para>Let's make our example a bit more complex:</para>

      <programlisting>@Entity
@Indexed
public class Place {
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue
    @DocumentId
    private Long id;

    @Field( index = Index.TOKENIZED )
    private String name;

    @OneToOne( cascade = { CascadeType.PERSIST, CascadeType.REMOVE } )
    <emphasis role="bold">@IndexedEmbedded</emphasis>
    private Address address;
    ....
}

@Entity
@Indexed
public class Address {
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue
    @DocumentId
    private Long id;

    @Field(index=Index.TOKENIZED)
    private String street;

    @Field(index=Index.TOKENIZED)
    private String city;

    <emphasis role="bold">@IndexedEmbedded(depth = 1, prefix = "ownedBy_")</emphasis>
    private Owner ownedBy;

    <emphasis role="bold">@ContainedIn</emphasis>
    @OneToMany(mappedBy="address")
    private Set&lt;Place&gt; places;
    ...
}

@Embeddable
public class Owner {
    @Field(index = Index.TOKENIZED)
    private String name;
   ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>Any <literal>@*ToOne</literal> and <literal>@Embedded</literal>
      attribute can be annotated with <literal>@IndexedEmbedded</literal>. The
      attributes of the associated class will then be added to the main entity
      index. In the previous example, the index will contain the following
      fields</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>id</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>name</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>address.street</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>address.city</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>addess.ownedBy_name</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>The default prefix is <literal>propertyName.</literal>, following
      the traditional object navigation convention. You can override it using
      the <literal>prefix</literal> attribute as it is shown on the
      <literal>ownedBy</literal> property.</para>

      <para><literal>depth</literal> is necessary when the object graph
      contains a cyclic dependency of classes (not instances). For example, if
      <classname>Owner</classname> points to <classname>Place</classname>.
      Hibernate Search will stop including Indexed embedded atttributes after
      reaching the expected depth (or the object graph boundaries are
      reached). A class having a self reference is an example of cyclic
      dependency. In our example, because <literal>depth</literal> is set to
      1, any <literal>@IndexedEmbedded</literal> attribute in Owner (if any)
      will be ignored.</para>

      <para>Such a feature (<literal>@IndexedEmbedded</literal>) is very
      useful to express queries refering to associated objects, such
      as:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Return places where name contains JBoss and where address city
          is Atlanta. In Lucene query this would be</para>

          <programlisting>+name:jboss +address.city:atlanta  </programlisting>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Return places where name contains JBoss and where owner's name
          contain Joe. In Lucene query this would be</para>

          <programlisting>+name:jboss +address.orderBy_name:joe  </programlisting>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      <para>In a way it mimics the relational join operation in a more
      efficient way (at the cost of data duplication). Remember that, out of
      the box, Lucene indexes have no notion of association, the join
      operation is simply non-existent. It might help to keep the relational
      model normalzed while benefiting from the full text index speed and
      feature richness.</para>

      <para><note>
          <para>An associated object can itself be (but don't have to)
          <literal>@Indexed</literal></para>
        </note></para>

      <para>When @IndexedEmbedded points to an entity, the association has to
      be directional and the other side has to be annotated
      <literal>@ContainedIn</literal> (as see in the previous example). If
      not, Hibernate Search has no way to update the root index when the
      associated entity is updated (in ou example, a <literal>Place</literal>
      index document has to be updated when the associated
      <classname>Address</classname> instance is updated.</para>

      <note>
        <para><literal>@IndexedEmbedded</literal> is supported on collections
        too (ie to index associated object included in collections). But the
        support is only partially implemented. It will depend on how you
        update collections (Check HSEARCH-56 in JIRA for more informations).
        The workaround is to manually index the object
        (session.index())</para>
      </note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Boost factor</title>

      <para>Lucene has the notion of <emphasis>boost factor</emphasis> . It's
      a way to give more weigth to a field or to an indexed element over an
      other during the indexation process. You can use
      <literal>@Boost</literal> at the field or the class level.</para>

      <programlisting>@Entity
@Indexed(index="indexes/essays")
<emphasis role="bold">@Boost(2)</emphasis>
public class Essay {
    ...

    @Id
    @DocumentId
    public Long getId() { return id; }

    @Field(name="Abstract", index=Index.TOKENIZED, store=Store.YES)
    <emphasis role="bold">@Boost(2.5f)</emphasis>
    public String getSummary() { return summary; }

    @Lob
    @Field(index=Index.TOKENIZED)
    public String getText() { return text; }
}        </programlisting>

      <para>In our example, Essay's probability to reach the top of the search
      list will be multiplied by 2 and the summary field will be 2.5 more
      important than the test field. Note that this explaination is actually
      wrong, but it is simple and close enought to the reality. Please check
      the Lucene documentation or the excellent <citetitle>Lucene In Action
      </citetitle> from Otis Gospodnetic and Erik Hatcher.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Analyser</title>

      <para>The default analyzer class used to index the elements is
      configurable through the <literal>hibernate.search.analyzer</literal>
      property. If none defined,
      <classname>org.apache.lucene.analysis.standard.StandardAnalyzer</classname>
      is used as the default.</para>

      <para>You can also define the analyzer class per entity, per property
      and even per @Field (useful when multiple fields are indexed from a
      single proeprty).</para>

      <programlisting>@Entity
@Indexed
@Analyzer(impl = EntityAnalyzer.class)
public class MyEntity {
    @Id
    @GeneratedValue
    @DocumentId
    private Integer id;

    @Field(index = Index.TOKENIZED)
    private String name;

    @Field(index = Index.TOKENIZED)
    @Analyzer(impl = PropertyAnalyzer.class)
    private String summary;

    @Field(index = Index.TOKENIZED, analyzer = @Analyzer(impl = FieldAnalyzer.class)
    private String body;

    ...
}</programlisting>

      <para>In this example, <classname>EntityAnalyzer</classname> is used
      index all tokenized properties (eg. <literal>name</literal>), except for
      <literal>summary</literal> and <literal>body</literal> which are indexed
      with <classname>PropertyAnalyzer</classname> and
      <classname>FieldAnalyzer</classname> respectively.</para>

      <caution>
        <para>Mixing different analyzers in the same entity is most of the
        time a bad practice. It makes query building more complex and results
        less predictable (for the novice), especially if you are using a
        QueryParser (which uses the same analyzer for the whole query). As a
        thumb rule, the same analyzer should be used for both the indexing and
        the query for a given field.</para>
      </caution>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="search-mapping-bridge">
    <title>Property/Field Bridge</title>

    <para>In Lucene all index fields have to be represented as
    Strings. For this reason all entity properties annotated with <literal>@Field</literal> 
    have to be indexed in a String form. For
    most of your properties, Hibernate Search does the translation job for you
    thanks to a built-in set of bridges. In some cases, though you need a more fine
    grain control over the translation process.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Built-in bridges</title>

      <para><literal>Hibernate Search</literal> comes bundled with a set of
      built-in bridges between a Java property type and its full text
      representation.</para>

      <para><literal>Null</literal> elements are not indexed (Lucene does not
      support null elements and it does not make much sense either)</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>null</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>null elements are not indexed. Lucene does not support null
            elements and this does not make much sense either.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>java.lang.String</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>String are indexed as is</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>short, Short, integer, Integer, long, Long, float, Float,
          double, Double, BigInteger, BigDecimal</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Numbers are converted in their String representation. Note
            that numbers cannot be compared by Lucene (ie used in ranged
            queries) out of the box: they have to be padded <footnote>
                <para>Using a Range query is debatable and has drawbacks, an
                alternative approach is to use a Filter query which will
                filter the result query to the appropriate range.</para>

                <para>Hibernate Search will support a padding mechanism</para>
              </footnote></para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>

        <varlistentry>
          <term>java.util.Date</term>

          <listitem>
            <para>Dates are stored as yyyyMMddHHmmssSSS in GMT time
            (200611072203012 for Nov 7th of 2006 4:03PM and 12ms EST). You
            shouldn't really bother with the internal format. What is
            important is that when using a DateRange Query, you should know
            that the dates have to be expressed in GMT time.</para>

            <para>Usually, storing the date up to the milisecond is not
            necessary. <literal>@DateBridge</literal> defines the appropriate
            resolution you are willing to store in the index ( <literal>
            <literal>@DateBridge(resolution=Resolution.DAY)</literal>
            </literal> ). The date pattern will then be truncated
            accordingly.</para>

            <programlisting>@Entity 
@Indexed
public class Meeting {
    @Field(index=Index.UN_TOKENIZED)
    <emphasis role="bold">@DateBridge(resolution=Resolution.MINUTE)</emphasis>
    private Date date;
    ...                 </programlisting>

            <warning>
              <para>A Date whose resolution is lower than
              <literal>MILLISECOND</literal> cannot be a
              <literal>@DocumentId</literal></para>
            </warning>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Custom Bridge</title>

      <para>It can happen that the built-in bridges of Hibernate Search do
      not cover some of your property types, or that the String representation
      used is not what you expect. The following paragraphs sveral solutions for this
      problem.</para>

      <section>
        <title>StringBridge</title>

        <para>The simpliest custom solution is to give <productname>Hibernate
        Search </productname> an implementation of your expected
        <emphasis>object to String</emphasis> bridge. To do so you need to
        implements the
        <literal>org.hibernate.search.bridge.StringBridge</literal>
        interface</para>

        <programlisting>/**
 * Padding Integer bridge.
 * All numbers will be padded with 0 to match 5 digits
 *
 * @author Emmanuel Bernard
 */
public class PaddedIntegerBridge implements <emphasis role="bold">StringBridge</emphasis> {

    private int PADDING = 5;

    <emphasis role="bold">public String objectToString(Object object)</emphasis> {
        String rawInteger = ( (Integer) object ).toString();
        if (rawInteger.length() &gt; PADDING) 
            throw new IllegalArgumentException( "Try to pad on a number too big" );
        StringBuilder paddedInteger = new StringBuilder( );
        for ( int padIndex = rawInteger.length() ; padIndex &lt; PADDING ; padIndex++ ) {
            paddedInteger.append('0');
        }
        return paddedInteger.append( rawInteger ).toString();
    }
}                </programlisting>

        <para>Then any property or field can use this bridge thanks to the
        <literal>@FieldBridge</literal> annotation</para>

        <programlisting><emphasis role="bold">@FieldBridge(impl = PaddedIntegerBridge.class)</emphasis>
private Integer length;                </programlisting>

        <para>Parameters can be passed to the Bridge implementation making it
        more flexible. The Bridge implementation implements a
        <classname>ParameterizedBridge</classname> interface, and the
        parameters are passed through the <literal>@FieldBridge</literal>
        annotation.</para>

        <programlisting>public class PaddedIntegerBridge implements StringBridge, <emphasis
            role="bold">ParameterizedBridge</emphasis> {

    public static String PADDING_PROPERTY = "padding";
    private int padding = 5; //default

    <emphasis role="bold">public void setParameterValues(Map parameters)</emphasis> {
        Object padding = parameters.get( PADDING_PROPERTY );
        if (padding != null) this.padding = (Integer) padding;
    }

    public String objectToString(Object object) {
        String rawInteger = ( (Integer) object ).toString();
        if (rawInteger.length() &gt; padding) 
            throw new IllegalArgumentException( "Try to pad on a number too big" );
        StringBuilder paddedInteger = new StringBuilder( );
        for ( int padIndex = rawInteger.length() ; padIndex &lt; padding ; padIndex++ ) {
            paddedInteger.append('0');
        }
        return paddedInteger.append( rawInteger ).toString();
    }
}


//property
@FieldBridge(impl = PaddedIntegerBridge.class,
             <emphasis role="bold">params = @Parameter(name="padding", value="10")</emphasis>
            )
private Integer length;                </programlisting>

        <para>The <classname>ParameterizedBridge</classname> interface can be
        implemented by <classname>StringBridge</classname> ,
        <classname>TwoWayStringBridge</classname> ,
        <classname>FieldBridge</classname> implementations (see
        bellow).</para>

        <para>If you expect to use your bridge implementation on for an id
        property (ie annotated with <literal>@DocumentId</literal> ), you need
        to use a slightly extended version of <literal>StringBridge</literal>
        named <classname>TwoWayStringBridge</classname> . <literal>Hibernate
        Search </literal> needs to read the string representation of the
        identifier and generate the object out of it. There is not difference
        in the way the <literal>@FieldBridge</literal> annotation is
        used.</para>

        <programlisting>public class PaddedIntegerBridge implements TwoWayStringBridge, ParameterizedBridge {

    public static String PADDING_PROPERTY = "padding";
    private int padding = 5; //default

    public void setParameterValues(Map parameters) {
        Object padding = parameters.get( PADDING_PROPERTY );
        if (padding != null) this.padding = (Integer) padding;
    }

    public String objectToString(Object object) {
        String rawInteger = ( (Integer) object ).toString();
        if (rawInteger.length() &gt; padding) 
            throw new IllegalArgumentException( "Try to pad on a number too big" );
        StringBuilder paddedInteger = new StringBuilder( );
        for ( int padIndex = rawInteger.length() ; padIndex &lt; padding ; padIndex++ ) {
            paddedInteger.append('0');
        }
        return paddedInteger.append( rawInteger ).toString();
    }

    <emphasis role="bold">public Object stringToObject(String stringValue)</emphasis> {
        return new Integer(stringValue);
    }
}


//id property
@DocumentId
@FieldBridge(impl = PaddedIntegerBridge.class,
             params = @Parameter(name="padding", value="10") 
private Integer id;
                </programlisting>

        <para>It is critically important for the two-way process to be
        idempotent (ie object = stringToObject( objectToString( object ) )
        ).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>FieldBridge</title>

        <para>Some usecase requires more than a simple object to string
        translation when mapping a property to a Lucene index. To give you
        most of the flexibility you can also implement a bridge as a
        <classname>FieldBridge</classname> . This interface give you a
        property value and let you map it the way you want in your Lucene
        <classname>Document</classname> .This interface is very similar in its
        concept to the <productname>Hibernate</productname>
        <classname>UserType</classname> .</para>

        <para>You can for example store a given property in two different
        document fields</para>

        <programlisting>/**
 * Store the date in 3 different field year, month, day
 * to ease Range Query per year, month or day
 * (eg get all the elements of december for the last 5 years)
 *
 * @author Emmanuel Bernard
 */
public class DateSplitBridge implements FieldBridge {
    private final static TimeZone GMT = TimeZone.getTimeZone("GMT");

    <emphasis role="bold">public void set(String name, Object value, Document document, Field.Store
            store, Field.Index index, Float boost) {
                    </emphasis>
        Date date = (Date) value;
        Calendar cal = GregorianCalendar.getInstance( GMT );
        cal.setTime( date );
        int year = cal.get( Calendar.YEAR );
        int month = cal.get( Calendar.MONTH ) + 1;
        int day = cal.get( Calendar.DAY_OF_MONTH );
        //set year
        Field field = new Field( name + ".year", String.valueOf(year), store, index );
        if ( boost != null ) field.setBoost( boost );
        document.add( field );
        //set month and pad it if needed
        field = new Field( name + ".month", month &lt; 10 ? "0" : "" + String.valueOf(month), store, index);
        if ( boost != null ) field.setBoost( boost );
        document.add( field );
        //set day and pad it if needed
        field = new Field( name + ".day", day &lt; 10 ? "0" : "" + String.valueOf(day), store, index );
        if ( boost != null ) field.setBoost( boost );
        document.add( field );
    }
}


//property
<emphasis role="bold">@FieldBridge(impl = DateSplitBridge.class)</emphasis>
private Integer length;                </programlisting>

        <para></para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>