<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ Hibernate, Relational Persistence for Idiomatic Java
  ~
  ~  Copyright (c) 2010, Red Hat, Inc. and/or its affiliates or third-party contributors as
  ~  indicated by the @author tags or express copyright attribution
  ~  statements applied by the authors.  All third-party contributions are
  ~  distributed under license by Red Hat, Inc.
  ~
  ~  This copyrighted material is made available to anyone wishing to use, modify,
  ~  copy, or redistribute it subject to the terms and conditions of the GNU
  ~  Lesser General Public License, as published by the Free Software Foundation.
  ~  
  ~  This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~  but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~  or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~  for more details.
  ~
  ~  You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~  along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~  Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~  51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~  Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../hsearch.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<chapter id="search-architecture">
  <title>Architecture</title>

  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>

    <para>Hibernate Search consists of an indexing and an index search
    component. Both are backed by Apache Lucene.</para>

    <para>Each time an entity is inserted, updated or removed in/from the
    database, Hibernate Search keeps track of this event (through the
    Hibernate event system) and schedules an index update. All the index
    updates are handled without you having to use the Apache Lucene APIs (see
    <xref linkend="search-configuration-event" />).</para>

    <para>To interact with Apache Lucene indexes, Hibernate Search has the
    notion of <classname>DirectoryProvider</classname>s. A directory provider
    will manage a given Lucene <classname>Directory</classname> type. You can
    configure directory providers to adjust the directory target (see <xref
    linkend="search-configuration-directory" />).</para>

    <para>Hibernate Search uses the Lucene index to search an entity and
    return a list of managed entities saving you the tedious object to Lucene
    document mapping. The same persistence context is shared between Hibernate
    and Hibernate Search. As a matter of fact, the
    <classname>FullTextSession</classname> is built on top of the Hibernate
    Session so that the application code can use the unified
    <classname>org.hibernate.Query</classname> or
    <classname>javax.persistence.Query</classname> APIs exactly the same way a
    HQL, JPA-QL or native query would do.</para>

    <para>To be more efficient Hibernate Search batches the write interactions
    with the Lucene index. There are currently two types of batching. Outside
    a transaction, the index update operation is executed right after the
    actual database operation. This is really a no batching setup. In the case
    of an ongoing transaction, the index update operation is scheduled for the
    transaction commit phase and discarded in case of transaction rollback.
    The batching scope is the transaction. There are two immediate
    benefits:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Performance: Lucene indexing works better when operation are
        executed in batch.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>ACIDity: The work executed has the same scoping as the one
        executed by the database transaction and is executed if and only if
        the transaction is committed. This is not ACID in the strict sense of
        it, but ACID behavior is rarely useful for full text search indexes
        since they can be rebuilt from the source at any time.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You can think of those two batch modes (no scope vs transactional)
    as the equivalent of the (infamous) autocommit vs transactional behavior.
    From a performance perspective, the <emphasis>in transaction</emphasis>
    mode is recommended. The scoping choice is made transparently. Hibernate
    Search detects the presence of a transaction and adjust the scoping.<tip>
        <para>It is recommended - for both your database and Hibernate Search
        - to execute your operations in a transaction, be it JDBC or JTA.
        </para>
      </tip></para>

    <note>
       Hibernate Search works perfectly fine in the Hibernate / EntityManager long conversation pattern aka. atomic conversation. 
    </note>

    <note>
       Depending on user demand, additional scoping will be considered, the pluggability mechanism being already in place. 
    </note>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Back end</title>

    <para>Hibernate Search offers the ability to let the batched work being
    processed by different back ends. Three back ends are provided out of the
    box and you have the option to plugin in your own implementation.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Back end types</title>

      <section>
        <title>Lucene</title>

        <para>In this mode, all index update operations applied on a given
        node (JVM) will be executed to the Lucene directories (through the
        directory providers) by the same node. This mode is typically used in
        non clustered environment or in clustered environments where the
        directory store is shared.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="lucene-backend.png"
                       format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata align="center" depth="" fileref="lucene-backend.png"
                       format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="12cm" />
          </imageobject>

          <caption>
            <para>Lucene back end configuration.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>This mode targets non clustered applications, or clustered
        applications where the Directory is taking care of the locking
        strategy.</para>

        <para>The main advantage is simplicity and immediate visibility of the
        changes in Lucene queries (a requirement in some applications).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>JMS</title>

        <para>All index update operations applied on a given node are sent to
        a JMS queue. A unique reader will then process the queue and update
        the master index. The master index is then replicated on a regular
        basis to the slave copies. This is known as the master/slaves pattern.
        The master is the sole responsible for updating the Lucene index. The
        slaves can accept read as well as write operations. However, they only
        process the read operation on their local index copy and delegate the
        update operations to the master.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata align="center" fileref="jms-backend.png" format="PNG" />
          </imageobject>

          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata align="center" depth="" fileref="jms-backend.png"
                       format="PNG" scalefit="1" width="12cm" />
          </imageobject>

          <caption>
            <para>JMS back end configuration.</para>
          </caption>
        </mediaobject>

        <para>This mode targets clustered environments where throughput is
        critical, and index update delays are affordable. Reliability is
        ensured by the JMS provider and by having the slaves working on a
        local copy of the index.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>JGroups</title>

        <para>The JGroups based back end works similar to the JMS one and is
        designed after the same master/slave pattern. However, instead of JMS
        the JGroups toolkit is used as a replication mechanism. This back end
        can be used as an alternative to JMS when response time is critical,
        but i.e. JNDI service is not available.</para>
      </section>

      <note>Hibernate Search is an extensible architecture. Feel free to drop
      ideas for other third party back ends to<literal>
      hibernate-dev@lists.jboss.org</literal>.</note>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Work execution</title>

      <para>The indexing work (done by the back end) can be executed
      synchronously with the transaction commit (or update operation if out of
      transaction), or asynchronously.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Synchronous</title>

        <para>This is the safe mode where the back end work is executed in
        concert with the transaction commit. Under highly concurrent
        environment, this can lead to throughput limitations (due to the
        Apache Lucene lock mechanism) and it can increase the system response
        time if the backend is significantly slower than the transactional
        process and if a lot of IO operations are involved.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Asynchronous</title>

        <para>This mode delegates the work done by the back end to a different
        thread. That way, throughput and response time are (to a certain
        extend) decorrelated from the back end performance. The drawback is
        that a small delay appears between the transaction commit and the
        index update and a small overhead is introduced to deal with thread
        management.</para>

        <para>It is recommended to use synchronous execution first and
        evaluate asynchronous execution if performance problems occur and
        after having set up a proper benchmark.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="search-architecture-readerstrategy" xreflabel="Reader strategy">
    <title>Reader strategy</title>

    <para>When executing a query, Hibernate Search interacts with the Apache
    Lucene indexes through a reader strategy. Choosing a reader strategy will
    depend on the profile of the application (frequent updates, read mostly,
    asynchronous index update etc). See also <xref
    linkend="configuration-reader-strategy" /></para>

    <section>
      <title>Shared</title>

      <para>With this strategy, Hibernate Search will share the same
      <classname>IndexReader</classname>, for a given Lucene index, across
      multiple queries and threads provided that the
      <classname>IndexReader</classname> is still up-to-date. If the
      <classname>IndexReader</classname> is not up-to-date, a new one is
      opened and provided. Each <classname>IndexReader</classname> is made of
      several <classname>SegmentReader</classname>s. This strategy only
      reopens segments that have been modified or created after last opening
      and shares the already loaded segments from the previous instance. This
      strategy is the default.</para>

      <para>The name of this strategy is <literal>shared</literal>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Not-shared</title>

      <para>Every time a query is executed, a Lucene
      <classname>IndexReader</classname> is opened. This strategy is not the
      most efficient since opening and warming up an
      <classname>IndexReader</classname> can be a relatively expensive
      operation.</para>

      <para>The name of this strategy is <literal>not-shared</literal>.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Custom</title>

      <para>You can write your own reader strategy that suits your application
      needs by implementing
      <classname>org.hibernate.search.reader.ReaderProvider</classname>. The
      implementation must be thread safe.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
